[SPEAKER_04]: So, is there any specific questions or any surprise questions?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, we thought to bring up this sutta called the Relay Chariots.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's where Venerable Sariputta, he hears of a monk praised by other monks, and so he decides to go and visit him.
[SPEAKER_04]: And his name is Venerable Puñña.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he eventually finds Venerable Puñña and then asks him a few questions.
[SPEAKER_04]: He says, my friend, is the holy life lived under the blessed one?
[SPEAKER_05]: And pañña replies, yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is the holy life lived under the blessed one for the sake of purity in terms of virtue?
[SPEAKER_04]: He says, no, that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, is the holy life lived for the sake of purity in terms of mind?
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: And for the sake of what, then, is the whole life lived under the blessed one?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's about knowledge and vision, or whatever the utmost goal is, which is nibbāna, of course.
[SPEAKER_04]: Virtue is not necessary.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're just nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just let go of things.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll start at the end.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll have non-attachment now.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't care about things anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is quite normal.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a quite normal view.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll just start at the end.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll be like an arahant.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you can't get to the end.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't reach that destination without, you know, getting there, walking there, traveling.
[SPEAKER_04]: So the simile that is given is the relay chariots.
[SPEAKER_04]: And this is the simile that Puññā is giving to Sariputta, so that he can understand what he's saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: He says, So, my friend, I will give you an analogy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suppose that while King of Kosala was staying at Sarvati, some urgent business were to arise at Saketa, and that between Sarvati and Saketa, seven relay chariots were made ready for him.
[SPEAKER_04]: Coming out of the door of the inner palace in Sarvati, he would get in the first relay chariot.
[SPEAKER_04]: By means of the first relay chariot, he would reach the second.
[SPEAKER_04]: Getting out of the first relay chariot, he would get into the second.
[SPEAKER_04]: And by means of the second, and so forth, he would, eh... Getting out of the sixth relay chariot, he would get into the seventh.
[SPEAKER_04]: And by means of the seventh, he would finally arrive at the door of the inner palace at Sargeta.
[SPEAKER_04]: Complete dispassion, disenchantment, relinquishment, cessation, freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the goal.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he doesn't practice for the sake of purifying the virtue only.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, without purifying the virtue, he won't be able to practice for the purification of mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means then, he won't be able to practice for the purification of views, for the purification of freedom from doubt, for the purification...
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, unless he starts with the first chariot, he won't be arriving at the goal.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, none of the chariots are the goal, but without them, the goal would not simply exist.
[SPEAKER_03]: And in the same sense, then, when the king did arrive, when they asked him, well, did you come by the means of this chariot?
[SPEAKER_03]: He said, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: I came by the means of chariot after chariot after chariot after chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I'm done.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how I reached this place.
[SPEAKER_04]: They say, well, he abandoned the first chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he doesn't need his virtue anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, he doesn't need to purify it anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's his purity of virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you lack purity of virtue, you need to work on that chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you don't like it, you can drop the work, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: you can drop the chariot, because virtue now, it's there, developed.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's why it's purification of virtue that leads to the purification of mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't drop your mind either, when you finish with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can certainly drop investing further effort and work in purifying it, because it has been purified.
[SPEAKER_03]: Polishing a brass plate or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: When it's clean and polished, well, stop polishing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, you can carry on if you want to, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's then the question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, so is that the purpose?
[SPEAKER_03]: To just polish for the sake of polishing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's to move on to the next one that needs now work on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you have to recognize there's further to go.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't have the idea of where you're going... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: There has to be a unifying... like, you know, the king wanted to get to that other town.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, everything else was arranged to support that goal.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that is... the whole point is to keep, as we always say, the reasons for practice, the intentions behind your actions, keep that in the mind, because then you know why you are keeping the virtue, why you're making the effort to be sense-restrained, why you're making... guarding of the sense doors and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you ignore your goal, then it's just... it can become... this can become a goal in itself, which means you won't be purifying your virtue anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will be assuming it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will be holding it on the level of
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, well, this practice is about worshipping the first chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about glorifying it, it's about riding every now and then, but never leaving it to go into the next one, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: never completing that work, never committing to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the purification of virtue is not something you just take on, on account of authority, or tradition, or teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something you have to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when you do it, then you won't need an external authority, tradition or a teacher to tell you about virtue or not, because you purified it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why purification of virtue has to lead you to the purification of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, purification of virtue, that you have to do, have to purify, have to keep an eye on, have to develop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, when the Buddha says, oh, he becomes accomplished in virtue,
[SPEAKER_03]: whereby no unwholesome states can cause fear in him, because he knows that his virtue is accomplished.
[SPEAKER_03]: He knows he won't break the virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter what comes, what challenges, what pressures him.
[SPEAKER_03]: That means accomplished in virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: That means virtue has been purified to the to the degree necessary to move on to the second chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why purification of that accomplishment, that virtue, results in factual samādhi, as we said before in quote to those other suttas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, oh, my virtue is unbroken, it's accomplished, no fear, nothing can perturb my mind on account of... Would I do that or not?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you know what you will not do, and you've been practicing that diligently, ardently, and now, you recognize that, no, doesn't matter what comes, these things will not be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, purification of the virtue, then, becomes accomplished.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's already the form of samādhi, which is, again, exactly why it would lead to, then, the second step of purifying the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, purification of virtue, of course, sense restraint, precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there anything else?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is it just keeping the precepts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just adhere to the precepts and you're purifying your virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would that be enough?
[SPEAKER_05]: What would you need to do?
[SPEAKER_05]: Abandon the assumption of sīla-pāra of past.
[SPEAKER_05]: How do you do that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, it's understanding why the why wholesome is wholesome and why unwholesome is unwholesome, in the sense of, in relation to the... How do you do that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, I suppose this this idea of
[SPEAKER_03]: If you start with purification of virtue, so you don't start with, you know...
[SPEAKER_03]: Understanding of the dhamma and all the other things that will kind of provide you with the answers, you start with purification of virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you abandon sīla-bhāta-paramāsa just by the means of virtue?
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think that's why you have to have this final... Well, actually, you can.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha did say puthujjana can free himself from sīla-bhāta-paramāsa without a final goal.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's an assumption.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is then that which a puthujjana can do, let alone somebody who knows the Buddha's teaching,
[SPEAKER_03]: In regard to the keeping the precepts that will actually free him from sīlabhāta paramāsa, needing the tradition, needing the authority, needing the teacher, they would free him from any external kind of criteria he would see for himself, the purification of virtue and the accomplishment of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the single factor that's absent in the one who doesn't see it and present in the one who sees it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Understanding the intention behind.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the single factor behind that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you understand intention?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing... attending, correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, but even that requires the same responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to take responsibility for what you're doing, including taking on the precept.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not an external commandment to any, to the slightest degree, it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you need external authority, traditions, senior agents or whatever, to keep you together from breaking precepts, you're not purifying anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just have enough foresight to place yourself in the environment that will force you to not misbehave.
[SPEAKER_03]: But even that, it's only going to be relative.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to be doing it yourself and take responsibility for that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm keeping the precepts because I want to purify the virtue, because I want to purify the mind, because I want to purify the views, the doubt, the knowledge and vision of what's path, what it isn't path, the knowledge of the path, the nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: I want to be free from suffering once and for all.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, if Ajahn comes and says, no, no, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not against the vinaya.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not a criteria for you to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If Ajahn comes and says, oh, you mustn't do that, well, that's again not a criteria for you to not do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The criteria is the knowledge of the precepts and then that exactly responsibility for keeping the precepts is taken.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is why I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're gonna feel the kind of the
[SPEAKER_03]: The closeness of the possibility of, oh, so I could break it with no repercussions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when you need to start contemplating the danger and really consider, like, okay, but am I doing... Why do I even want to practice in the first place?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is my motivation?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are my reasons?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because according to what I want to practice, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: the Buddha's instruction, I should be able to do it by myself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it concerns only me, and if I need an external authority, tradition, the way how things were done, or some very, like, inspiring, you know, non-compromising teacher to keep me together, well, that is... that is no practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's... if somebody has nothing, and that can make them keep the precepts, fine.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's better than not keeping the precepts at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in and of itself, that's exactly what's still about the Paramahasaya is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Precepts have been taken, duty has been taken, but responsibility for it has been covered up, avoided, dismissed.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, no purification of virtue means there will be no samādhi, even if you keep the precepts for 100 years.
[SPEAKER_03]: And consequently, also, purifying the virtue means there will be samādhi, even if you don't do any meditation techniques, which usually go hand in hand with not purifying the virtue, but keeping it on account of authority, or like a secondary kind of, okay, yeah, do this, because it's probably good for you on some level.
[SPEAKER_03]: But really, really, the meat of the practice is sensation watching, or nostril observation, or belly bhavana, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: First chariot leads you to the second one.
[SPEAKER_03]: Factual samādhi, factual purification of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you purify your mind through the concentration practices and focusing and ignoring what bothers you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, not according to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: You purify your mind by purifying your intentions, that are now revealed on account of having traveled with the first chariot as far as it goes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, on that subtle mental level, the intention of greed,
[SPEAKER_03]: Non-greed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aversion, non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Distraction, non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's as seen as the first, you know, crude, coarse precepts were in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whatever you're about to do, as the Buddha instructed Rāhula in that sutta, like with a similar mirror, well, you reflect against it, on having purified the virtue, not just pontificate around it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Having purified the virtue, you have intention to do this or that, say this or that, think this or that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, is this leading to my harm, harm of others?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it making the greed increase or decrease?
[SPEAKER_03]: An honour is in greed, come or not come.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same for aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you gotta... now, the traveling of the... with the second chariot, purification of the mind entails the purification and the clarity of the context of what's beneficial truly and what it's not truly beneficial.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is determined by where the intentions are rooted.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is factual samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is factual imperturbability.
[SPEAKER_01]: No need for focusing, no need for concentration, just wisdom and context.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know, big surprise.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, inevitably, if you have been purifying your intentions, not acting out of the unwholesome ones, it will lead you to the purification of the views.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you purify the views then?
[SPEAKER_05]: By re-establishing the one's own understanding of... Of what?
[SPEAKER_03]: What specifically?
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, how do you... how do you know you're traveling by a third chariot?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, I mean, like, literally, how do you know that you're in a third chariot, if you're in a chariot?
[SPEAKER_03]: By remembering that you traveled in the first one, and then the second one.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the principle of the first one, the principle of the second one, leads you to the principle of the third one.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, you, by that, by the time you're in a third chariot,
[SPEAKER_03]: You will pretty much already know what's important and what is not important, what constitutes the successful travel and what constitutes unsuccessful travel.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh... views... would then... any views that you... any views that might come up, would be already seen, to a degree, against that which you've been doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and that's why, as I said, like, if you put aside this specific sutta, sīla-bhāt-paramāsa, the purification virtue, can be done by somebody even with the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_03]: If they put the views aside, whatever views they have, they don't emphasize that.
[SPEAKER_03]: They emphasize taking on responsibility for behavior by body, speech, intentions of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they might have had the views still.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was in the past.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Will I be... Nibbāna is that.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is not the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: But regardless of what thinking they've been having, what views they've been revolving around, they did not emphasize that.
[SPEAKER_03]: They actually emphasized doing the restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Keeping the precepts, sensory strain, guarding, and taking responsibility for it, and enduring the weight of that responsibility, not just sort of misplacing it back onto the... oh, yeah, no, no, we're in this together, that's why we do this, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you feel... you feel lighter on account of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if they actually have been putting their views aside,
[SPEAKER_03]: And practice the purification of virtue and the purification of the mind, that in itself already constitutes the purification of the views.
[SPEAKER_03]: So now, when the views would come up, more specifically, well, they would already know not to put the emphasis on them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how you purify the views.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly why that leads you to going beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being unable to emphasize what cannot be emphasized.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being unable to pervert your... being unable to doubt that which precedes the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whichever way you want to put it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, oh, how do I become a Sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: What technique do I follow?
[SPEAKER_03]: What nāma, rūpa, viññāṇa, relationship I need to understand?
[SPEAKER_03]: Purify the virtue, purify your intentions, that will undo your views, that will make you go beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, exactly, the next chariot is, oh, he knows what the practice is and what the practice isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: He knows exactly what it would lead to nibbāna and what wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: He knows for himself.
[SPEAKER_03]: He sees it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the next chariot, if he follows that which leads to nibbāna, well, he knows what nibbāna is now.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's right there.
[SPEAKER_03]: The knowledge and vision.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this is important because
[SPEAKER_03]: The views come first in everyone's experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't change that.
[SPEAKER_03]: People would hope, okay, putting the views aside means these views will stop coming up for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, they won't.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can use your discernment to not allow yourself to emphasize them and act out of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, well, yeah, I think it's like this, or I think it's like that, I think it might be like this, but... Am I purifying the virtue?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I keeping the precepts, guarding all the sense doors?
[SPEAKER_03]: Have I taken responsibility?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I feeling the weight of my investment, so to speak, in this practice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or do I feel absolved because I found a greater, bigger thing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this community?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this religion?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this practice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this meditation center?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this technique?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this whatever?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the danger isn't in there being these views.
[SPEAKER_05]: The danger is sort of becoming intoxicated by them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, the danger is allowing yourself to shift back the emphasis onto the views.
[SPEAKER_03]: And kind of, oh, yes, yes, you know, vinaya and precepts, sure, you know, but really drift away from the... from the... from the... from the emphasis.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, from the emphasis on that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is, you know, you hear that, like you would see that, you know, people are like, yeah, yeah, eight precepts and stuff, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they're kind of brushed aside.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the factual thing, obvious to everyone, keeping the precepts of virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's just going to be now information about the views.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you hear people describe the practice, it's just people describing views and opinions.
[SPEAKER_03]: As towards this, which provides information, satisfying answer, not satisfying answer, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, yeah, okay, but how do I purify this virtue then, that then leads me to the purification of the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I purify these views?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I can take it or leave it, sure, but what do I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you know, consciousness never changes, it's always there, you just need to see it, be here now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but how do I do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, by seeing that consciousness is unchanging, by being here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you're just saying the same thing in different words.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I do it?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where are these chariots that I need to travel with?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the same when it comes to when people quote the suttas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah, see, anatta, it's anatta in this, anatta in that, anatta...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so how do you do it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, by seeing no self.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how do I do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: By seeing that you can't own things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, you're just giving the synonyms of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I do it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the Buddha didn't just come out of the blue and just said, listen, there's no self.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're done.
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole gradual training.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just keep the precepts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the next step now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Will the next step be on the level of, well, this is how you purify the precepts further?
[SPEAKER_03]: This is how you then see intention of your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or just like, oh, well, yeah, you keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, relax, watch your nostrils, get your kāmatana, focus on the objects, concentrate and concentrate and concentrate, and everything else will just... nibbāna, vijjāna,
[SPEAKER_03]: A diligent monk, does he sit watching his nostrils, feeling blissful?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: He purifies his mind on account of developing four foundations of mindfulness, and then he feels blissful, because he's deathless, because he's free from prison, his suffering cannot touch him.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, even then, as I said, when we started this, even the whole... like, he recollects his unbroken virtue, for which he'd taken responsibility,
[SPEAKER_03]: And he knows now, because he's taken responsibility, that he cannot break it.
[SPEAKER_03]: He'll never know that if he hasn't taken responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, well, I'm not breaking it here because these ājāns, you know, will kick me out and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, but what if my circumstances change?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do I know for sure then?
[SPEAKER_03]: When there is nobody to punish me or tell me off or fear or blame or something like that in this environment, if there is no such thing there, do I know for sure?
[SPEAKER_03]: I will still not do this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or if the circumstances change slightly, oh, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, what purification have you done?
[SPEAKER_02]: None.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a guy in prison who can't do, can't kill people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: As I said, circumstantially, it's better than allowing it to be done, but we're not talking about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like how layman should live his life, not the one who wants to practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the point is then, oh, if you've taken responsibility, the time, if you have invested effort, time will come.
[SPEAKER_03]: He knows.
[SPEAKER_03]: No matter the circumstances that are not in my control, what comes my way, what temptation, what pressure, what kind of things, discomforts, discontentment, accomplished in virtue means knowing that he will not do anything against their virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that gives rise to pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_05]: The samādhi.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's also this responsibility, I think, initially,
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, painful.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, so people... Of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: People who will... Well, there is a reason that people would willingly go into into a factor of sīla bhārata paramaṣa, willingly put it on there, because it actually, at this kind of immediate level, it makes it more pleasant for me, or makes it less unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in the long run,
[SPEAKER_05]: That prevents your progress.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's why I will give so much faith to this external form or this meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now that you mention faith, that's another equally misunderstood thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, faith means I'll just be brain-dead, devoted to the instruction of this person, as in inspiration that I get behind this instruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Faith means, put your view second, keep the virtue, guard the sense doors first.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you won't see a direct reason to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your views are telling you otherwise.
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole world is telling you otherwise.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you have enough faith in what you understood from what the Buddha instructed, so out of that faith, you don't revolve around, oh, what is nāmarūpa, and is this, and is that, and is that, oh, what is the etymology of this, what...
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You put all that aside, and you actually take responsibility for the virtue, and you got to sense those, and you pretty much maintain and develop and increase the wholesome context behind your intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Out of faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have no other reason other than faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll do this because it makes sense to that extent, and I have faith that the Buddha was right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me just
[SPEAKER_03]: Start doing this, while the views and all the answers I seek, and all the doubts and insecurities, I'll just put that second until I deal with these things first.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you could see how that faith could equally result in sotāpatti and arahantship, because you're actually doing the work.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it's very... that faith is very different to, like, inspiration.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I wanted to say as well is that about taking responsibility for virtue,
[SPEAKER_00]: It very much also pertains to being able even to purify the views by putting views aside, because you have to also
[SPEAKER_00]: Because views aren't usually something that you take responsibility for, or consciously even hold.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think this, and I think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're more just very fundamental, like assumptions about things that you take so much for granted, that you don't even take responsibility or realize that, you know, this is a view that I have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it means I could... it might not be right, or I could not have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's more subtle even than the responsibility for actions and things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you kind of need to start with that, which then sort of shows you that, oh, even these views that I hold, I am responsible for holding them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then let me...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't... let me put them aside, as you said, and continue to do this, which I see is beneficial, which will lead me in this direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: By putting the views aside and purifying virtue and purifying your mind, it does actually start to create a reference point for those views, which is a new view, sure, but it's the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the view that has arisen as a result of practice that has not been acting out of and emphasizing the views.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can see them as views.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: You get to see them.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're just blind to them being views.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that whole thing of, like, you cannot have the views, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't just drop them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't just choose to not hold them.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what you can do is choose to not prioritize them anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Out of faith, purify your virtue, purify your mind, and that will then diminish these views, which gives rise to what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, you would replace your wrong views with the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: A view that knows what the path is and what the path isn't.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like you also... you can't not have faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to have faith in something, whether it's drugs or escape or... Whatever you're finding your safety, whatever you're investing effort in maintaining your sense of safety, that is where you have your faith in.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever that is, whether it's sensuality, tradition, authority, family, possessions...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: In as much as the views are inevitable.
[SPEAKER_03]: A degree of faith and belief is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what is not inevitable is to lose your reason in regard to it, and not be aware of your situation within it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, and that will lead to faith, whereby that faith becomes wisdom?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Faith, basically, informed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Informed faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not faith on account of emotional experience and feeling that I have when I listen to this or read that.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's the way.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is factually good for me?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, to find a doctor who gives me an instruction, a recipe.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how will I know that's correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: How will I know that will cure me?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well,
[SPEAKER_03]: By initially taking it on faith and beginning the application of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Adhering to a diet, protecting of the wound, not increasing the infection and so on, out of faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, as your as your health improves on account of it, you won't have that faith anymore, because you saw for yourself that it cured you.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the faith...
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't lead to the end of faith, is intoxicating.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's like...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's basically a faith for which you haven't taken responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so I will continue to believe it because it's... Because it makes me feel better, makes me feel... well, makes me feel absolved from responsibility.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's incredibly dangerous because of that, because of that sort of intoxication.
[SPEAKER_03]: You willingly forsake your reason and discern it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't realize, okay, it's because it's pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that happens to people, especially, like, when it comes to, you know, following the instructions of others in the religion.
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of being intox... self-intoxicated by your own faith and avoiding responsibility, you neglected the obvious things that are wrong right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You ignored, you turned a blind eye, and then later on, sure, when things went too far, then it's like, oh, wow, yeah, I don't know how that happened.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like this charismatic leader, he looks like he's... or she looks like they... they got it sorted, so I'll just, you know...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'll just submit to nothing for myself.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even if that charismatic leader is the Buddha himself, he won't get you anywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when people did just follow him because he was so charismatic and inspiring, he dismissed them, he told them off.
[SPEAKER_03]: Told him to get lost, to stop following him, because they're not practicing what he said.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, those people, they didn't follow him, but actually fulfilled the teaching.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like in the suttas, when an arahant, when a person becomes an arahant, they free their mind, it's always sort of portrayed with a description of, ah, the teacher has been worshipped.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they truly... That's the only way to pay respect to the Buddha, is to fulfill his teachings.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I paid my respects.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I don't owe anything to anyone, including the Buddha himself.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, that's much, you know, more insecure, more full of doubt, requiring more of diligence, discomfort, endurance, than just, no, no, no, this is the greatest teaching, I'm a believer, I'm saved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Say, what you mentioned now, you have doubt coming up, and you have these views coming up.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in light of
[SPEAKER_03]: This discussion and this sutta, how do you deal with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you deal with the doubt and the mind and the insecurity and the anxiety and everything else?
[SPEAKER_03]: Views regarding around that and lack of answers.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you do in terms of what we just described?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, like in terms of what you've just described, if you have been taking on the
[SPEAKER_04]: See, the doubt as doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, doubt will be
[SPEAKER_01]: But wouldn't there be just another view that I have to do on account of the view?
[SPEAKER_05]: Potentially, but if you're enjoying it on the right level... Aha!
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's... that's what you do first.
[SPEAKER_03]: You endure it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_03]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_03]: It means not turning... We're back onto the second chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: What does that mean in terms of the second chariot?
[SPEAKER_03]: Enduring on the right level, what does that mean in terms of purification of the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, citta, nimitta, yoniso, manasikāra... Purification of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, greed, aversion, delusion, non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: What does that mean in those terms?
[SPEAKER_03]: Enduring on the right level.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Of what?
[SPEAKER_05]: Of the doubt, of the unpleasant, the displeasure of the...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, not acting out of greed or aversion or distraction in regard to discomfort of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you will be able to see that and not act out of it if you have been keeping the virtue and practicing sense of strength.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, otherwise...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what you do, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't engage with it on the level of the views, because, obviously, doubt will just feed more doubt if you act out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Which is not sīla, which is not the first chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not along those principles.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, of course, you might, you get, but then, wait, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I do what I have been doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is this intention rooted in, in this particular instance of this doubt or this anxiety?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why that other sutra says, you know, how does the monk free himself from hindrances, so from from mind kind of obsessed with sensuality, or your will, or doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not by doing this or that, but by seeing through with yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that which hinders you in terms of the sensual desire, you see through it and recognize that, oh, there's a beautiful object,
[SPEAKER_03]: And pleasure in regard to it, that I'm acting out of.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or in this case, oh, I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, so there is this beautiful object that besets me, and aversion towards it, that I'm acting out of.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by seeing through with that proper attention, he re-establishes the context.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what the Buddha was describing as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, in... we mentioned a number of times lately that the whole... the two types of thoughts that he decided to think wholesome, not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, when unwholesome comes up, so when hindrances come up, oh, I'll just...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll just...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll just focus on a part of my body until I forget about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you won't find that in the suttas for sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: What he did say he was doing was... ah, so when there is the thought of sensuality, or cruelty, or real will, and you could even say doubt or anxiety, he... that was there, but he did not attend to it wrongly, at the face value, with the attitude, I must get rid of this, I must act out of this, aversion towards this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead, no, I would just keep investing my effort on the level of the context.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, this thought of sensuality that's here,
[SPEAKER_03]: Has it been kind of leading to my harm or my benefit in the past?
[SPEAKER_03]: How about in the present?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it for my good or not?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it for benefit of others?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it helpful?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it pressuring?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it increasing of the weakness or the strength?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it increasing of dispassion or passion?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just by pondering on those things, in face of the sensual desire, sensual desire will subside.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that is really what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the real context of the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ill-will, cruelty, doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, sure, it would be important to know this, but I'm obviously now emotionally gripped by doubt and I want to get rid of the pain of it, which means any answers I'm seeking on account of doubt in mind will be secondary.
[SPEAKER_03]: All I'm doing is fueling the aversion towards pain and that's a hindrance in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I attend...
[SPEAKER_03]: I attend to it rightly or I see through it, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there is this doubt that at a face value is trying to make me act.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't act, I endure it and I see what's through it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, aversion to pain is the goal of this seemingly seeking for an answer that my mind is trying to overwhelm me with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whenever I was averse and acting out of pain, how did that result?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did that bring pain to increase or decrease?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did that overcome doubt once and for all or not?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did it lead to my harm, harm of others?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did it lead to composure or distraction?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, look, doubt is gone, because I basically...
[SPEAKER_03]: I undone the attitude that was underlying, hidden behind this doubt that I was trying to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_05]: But asking those questions that you've asked would be impossible if you're acting out of it, if you're...
[SPEAKER_05]: Being absorbed in the content.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody, again, somebody might hear this now, and they have experience of doubt, and then they say, I must enact out of doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: I must do what this ajahn said.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they start asking these questions, rooted in trying to get rid of doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, they will not be able to see through that and abandon that, unless they have already been purifying their mind on account of taking responsibility and purifying their virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it stays on the level of abstraction and abuse, even if it isn't so.
[SPEAKER_03]: But those people who have taken responsibility for the virtue, purified the virtue, accomplished themselves in it, purified the intentions behind their actions, purified their mind, developed samādhi on account of it, they will catch this pretty much soon, if not immediately.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, wait!
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, yeah, I shouldn't be getting rid of the doubt, but now I'm telling myself that I shouldn't be getting rid of the doubt in order to get rid of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, I will not act out of that intention.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I'll let doubt be there and I'll keep seeing through it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And by seeing through it, the mind becomes unhindered from that which hinders you.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it hinders you not because of itself, in and of itself, it hinders you because you had no perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It relates very much to faith as well, the right type of faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, for example, when you have... when there is doubt,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even any of the hindrances, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to not act out of that doubt, because, like, your whole mind and everything that you've been doing for years and years, and your only way of finding some solution to it, or finding, this will give me confidence, this will give me faith, this will give me more, you know, what I need in order to keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, you know, I need to find the answer to this, or I need to seek a reassurance, or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you need to not do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you need to, at some point, not seek safety in the things that you've been used to seeking safety in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no... Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't lead to safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's rooted in already being unsafe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it actually only... what you are... you know, the more you're asking for something to give you faith, the more you are actually diminishing your possibility of having any faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: The more of like... the more in a direction of non-responsibility you're traveling.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you're avoiding it and avoiding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're like cultivating doubt, not cultivating faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's very... and that's why faith is absolutely necessary, because there is nothing else, no external, no, you know, nobody else or nothing else can, you know, do it for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no confirmation except your own.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I think it pretty much would come down to that, wouldn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Even it's like, you know, like we talk about enduring things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, people understand that, but a number of people would not even understand that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you read the suttas and say, well, no, it's about dealing and doing stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, well, yeah, but how you go about it matters.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you say you need to endure things without acting out of it, basically, yeah, you need a degree of faith to not act out immediately.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just, just to that extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you see, okay, this is what I do.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't replay with thoughts of ugly, and ugly, and ugly, and concentrated nostrils.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: I see through it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I see that this is just a beautiful object, inducive of lust, for which I'm responsible.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you re-establish the context, the beautiful object remains standing there in the world, as the Buddha said, but there is no...
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you haven't had that initial faith to endure and not act out of this duty, you know, this is what I must do and address, which is all rooted in aversion towards that which making you feel uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, without that faith, you just won't be able to restrain.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't be able to not act.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, even if you're doing the enduring, you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you have faith, though, and not act out, and stay in that seemingly overwhelming position of, but I'm not dealing with this, but it needs to be dealt with, I need to endure it, out of faith, well, then the path can become apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's said even in the suttas, I think so in the Gūtara, that like a noble disciple, so one with the right view, maybe even sakadāgām
[SPEAKER_03]: He has not become an anāgāmī yet, because he lacks faith, to a degree.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, he doesn't lack faith in the Buddha and the teachings.
[SPEAKER_03]: But where does he... Well, he lacks faith, just to that kind of initial degree, to not act out of sensual thoughts or thoughts of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: To that extent, he's not freeing himself from sensual thoughts and thoughts of ill-will, because he acts out of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if not necessarily acting towards sensuality, he acts out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: He distracts himself, he dismisses it, he contemplates a subha to get rid of the pain behind the pressure of sensuality, not to just see the nature of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why I keep saying, like, it's actually better if you practice a subha or loving-kindness before your mind is gripped with lust or your will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not in response to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when I say practice before, I don't mean as a mindless technique and motion you go through.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Invoke the image of beautiful that would otherwise induce lust and start seeing that within that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Start seeing the ugly, the perilous, the dangerous, the hidden trap and the bait.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the context needs to be developed sufficiently enough so that it doesn't move when these thoughts are present.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the context moves when you act out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you act out of it when you don't have enough faith to endure the thoughts that are present without acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, to that extent, a noble disciple, if he lacks the faith that would enable him to not immediately
[SPEAKER_03]: Resolve the sensual desire, or get rid of the ill-willed thoughts, he won't be free from those things, because he's perpetuating them through his ignorant action.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it should be obvious to anybody listening to this or our talks, when we talk about endurance, it's not on the same level as bearing of the elements, you know, like the Yadu Suttas, they said, it's translated as endurance, but it's it's not the same word I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, also, endurance means I just bear things mindlessly like that sutta says.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you bear heat, cold, thirst, words of others mindlessly, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: When we talk about endurance, you realize, oh, it's a completely different level.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the endurance that pertains to abandoning all of the taints in that sutta.
[SPEAKER_03]: First, not acting out, having faith, and the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the whole point of that would then be like, okay,
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem is in me being affected.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if I act out of directly towards these things that affect me, I'm perpetuating the fact that I'm being affected.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, faith as a factor, then, it's not just existing in somebody before he becomes a sotāpanna and then he...
[SPEAKER_03]: Faith is a spiritual power, as the Buddha called it, which means, later on, you use the same faith to not act out of things immediately, to not get rid of them immediately, so that you can endure them, because already now you have confidence that enduring them on this level will lead to seeing through them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when you cease to be hindered by any of the things that are otherwise hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: That does not mean that those things cease to arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just means you're incapable of not seeing through them when they arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing them as hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing... Well, no, they're not hindrances anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing them as what used to hinder you when you attended to it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it says, if he does not attend rightly to the sign of the beautiful, sensual hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: If he attends rightly to the sign of the beautiful, no sensuality hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: And same goes for all the other hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, enduring things rightly would then result in purification of the views that will make you go beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's done on account of the second character, as we said, not acting out of intentions rooted in aversion, sensuality, ill-will, greed, all sorts of kind of layers of the same three principles.
[SPEAKER_03]: Distraction as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, distraction is also, like, quite often ends up being justified means of dealing with things.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll focus on sensations, so I'm distracted from the pressing image that bothers me and emotionally disturbs me.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll go in a state of, you know, neither here nor there, half asleep, because that's peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not thinking about what I'm subjected to is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: And people then conflate the successful meditation practice with successful degree of ignoring the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: This endurance that we're talking about, I think, is also integral to
[SPEAKER_05]: Mindfulness, in the sense that... like mindfulness of the body, mindfulness of feeling, they... these are discerned as a relationship to what is presently enduring, in terms of... if you... if you don't... if you think of mindfulness of the body in terms of turning that into an object, like my body is an object, that is not seeing the relationship between
[SPEAKER_05]: Whatever is, you know, occupying... whatever is in front of me, being determined by my beating heart or... How do I feel?
[SPEAKER_03]: While I'm seeing this, how do I feel while I'm hearing these words?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I feel while I'm bearing heat and cold?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I enduring the feeling on account of bearing the elements?
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's the relationship between the feeling and the bearing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't find the feeling in your senses where you're observing things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, unless you need to look at that background, peripheral, in regard to what's there in front of you, there is no mindfulness for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: In regards to not being, when you said not being able to act in certain ways, does that mean basically understanding wholesome as wholesome, or harmful as harmful, and beneficial as beneficial?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because why would one be unable to act?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you haven't been acting long enough, and you took responsibility for avoiding that act.
[SPEAKER_03]: Out of faith,
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, out of seeing, you benefit directly for yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, you're stopping, basically, to see... Well, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, the other six chariots don't come after the first one.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're already waiting there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you see what's in front of you, if you travel through this.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are already seeing the purification of your intentions on account of purifying your virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are seeing the purification of views later on, if you keep purifying your virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a... it's a good... it's... again, it's a good criteria to go by.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ask yourself, if, say, there is no authority, there is no immediate, like, tradition, family, even the law, would I still uphold the value
[SPEAKER_03]: Of sense-restraint, guarding of the sense-doors, not acting out and not breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I choose to do it and I've been choosing to do it for so long.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there is no other thing to prevent you from doing it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, there is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fear of jail.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being beaten up, retribution, being kicked out of what you deem to be yours, which you take part, all these things prevent you from doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Losing your life, too, doesn't count?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're all factual reasons, but none of those... all of those reasons, at the same time, yeah, it's good.
[SPEAKER_03]: They didn't force you to be virtuous, but at the same time, they also take away responsibility for that virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why virtue and duty, sīlabhāta-paramāsa, is a factual factor.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need it, but you don't need it as a fetter.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the difference I'm describing.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you don't take responsibility, it will be a fetter.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you feel fully justified, because virtue is always good, well, you feel fully justified in just worshipping the first chariot and not even sitting in it, let alone reaching the second one.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is exactly why people who are not free from Sīla Bhāgavatam would not see the purification of the mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: which is purification of intentions arisen at the time, not a blanket technique, concentration or approach that you can just have regardless of what state the mind is in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, so are you independent of the concrete circumstances you find yourself in?
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you can say yes to that, the more you are moving towards the noble ones, who are actually, factually independent, not only of circumstances, but even of the teachings.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the more your mind will be composed and gladdened and joyful on account of the unbroken virtue that I'm accomplished in.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whether I'm in the forest or in the city, things that I will not do,
[SPEAKER_03]: Remain clear and kind of immovable.
[SPEAKER_03]: The context of that remains immovable.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is something you train for.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not something that is, as again, people would kind of naively hope.
[SPEAKER_03]: You take on, through a tradition, through an authority,
[SPEAKER_03]: Do some sort of technique or practice or whatever, have a special experience and now you become unable to break your virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You become unable to break your virtue if you have cultivate non-breaking of it responsibly for sufficient period of time.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you start recognizing the factual samādhi that comes, the factual safety that comes as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not, oh, I was virtuous, so devas will protect me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, they might.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not something you see for yourself, nor can you see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: What you can see for yourself as a factual protection is mind unmoved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind cannot act and resist out of aversion as much as it be.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot turn against itself, as I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot turn around and bite me, if it's upset with the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot give me sleepless nights.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot give me suicidal depressive thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's been tamed, and it's been tamed by me, who's been avoiding acting in certain directions, and then guarding of the sense doors, and sustaining of the right context in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have been making the work, putting the work in there diligently.
[SPEAKER_03]: As a result of it, the mind is calm, and you see it, and you have a direct verification of why this is worth doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, not acting out, yeah?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's always the... comes down to that, the problem of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pressure to act out, and then acting out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, no, what I meant is that, like, you can't escape responsibility, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can not act in certain ways, because you don't want to go to jail, or don't want to be kicked out, or anything, but... You don't see anything more immediate.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can make any difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can always choose.
[SPEAKER_02]: In regard to whatever you choose, it's you who chooses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Theoretically, it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you speak about theory from the point of view of the third chariot, yes, but that's not seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: One thing is to say that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Another thing is, are you saying that on account of being already accomplished in virtue, when it will be factually true?
[SPEAKER_03]: Now it's not factually true.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's theoretically true, and it's good to strive for that, but it's not an answer, and it's not an explanation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it is an explanation, but it's not an answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will be in the third chariot if you travel with the first two.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you cannot not be in the third chariot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, but are you?
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's my point.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are always doing it, it's always on you, but that's not seen and that's not how it's practically lived.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, now, I gotta do this, regardless of the environment, and the tradition, and the requirements, and the expectations.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, if you do it like that, then you will then see the benefit for yourself there and then, wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome is unwholesome, regardless of the environment, regardless of the tradition.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why it's said, the one, the Sotāpanna, who has freed himself from Sīla Bhakti Paramahāsa, gone beyond doubt, he, like, even if the whole world says, oh, the Buddha's instruction was wrong, he'll know that the world is wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not because he's so blinded by the faith in the Buddha, but his direct verification.
[SPEAKER_03]: Amid suffering, amidst brink, basically, of existence, depression, overwhelming pain, he cannot suffer because of the purification he developed and the way he sees things now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not because of he got rid of all of this and nothing ever comes to bother him.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the confidence cannot be shaken because, I mean, this is it, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: When amidst of the life-threatening pain and fear and anxiety, the mind does not turn against you, or itself, you don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is nothing greater that can verify your success, in terms of practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all the Buddha teaches, and that's all he needs to teach, and that's all you need to know, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's what it all boils down to.